<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Octopress | SotoSeattle]]></title>
  <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/categories/octopress/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-18T21:00:27-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Javier Soto]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Installing Octopress at github.io]]></title>
    <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2014/10/20/Octopress-GH/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-20T11:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2014/10/20/Octopress-GH</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I am collecting posts from my previous blog, ideogrammatic.com, adding some new ones I have written over the last month and putting it all together in github.io as my personal blog.</p>

<p>I am using Octopress with a tweaked mnml theme and have got hold of a nice domain with my handle sotoseattle to point to.</p>

<p>The basic deployment of an Octopress blog into your github.io is easy, and there are many posts with the details in the Internet so I am assuming you have gone through the paces.</p>

<p>Now, if you are like me, you’ll hit problems in unexpected places. I have found that it helps to understand how Octopress and GitHub actually use git repos between them.</p>

<p>In essence you’ll end up using two different git repos inside both your Octopress code base. And the fun part is that both point to the same github repo!</p>

<p>1.- the first can be found inside the folder _deploy:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code>rake generate</code> compiles the site from all the files in the source directory (and other resources) and places everything inside the _deploy folder.</li>
  <li><code>rake deploy</code> pushes it (the files inside _deploy) up to GitHub, actually to the to origin/master branch.</li>
</ul>

<p>So, for example, if we have a custom domain and we want it to point to our github.io site, we need a CNAME file that we place inside the source folder. After rake generate and rake deploy, it will show up in the root of origin/master (and inside our _deploy folder)</p>

<p>2.- The second git repo, you create it on the root:</p>

<p>For this one we create a single branch, “source”, that holds everything (all files, source and _deploy) and we push only to origin/source. Aha!, this repo goes to the ‘source’ branch in github, the generated one goes to ‘master’. So we don’t have a master branch in this local git repo, only source, and in this way we avoid pushing it to master in origin (which already tracks the first repo!).</p>

<p>Messy explanation, I know, but once you wrap your mind around the concept of 2 different repos pointing to 2 branches of the same upstream repo, it all makes sense.</p>

<p>Now, I may be off base in this explanation, if so, please set me straight in the comments.</p>

<p>Good luck with the Octos!</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/Oct14/octocat_octopress.png" width="400" title="Code Fellows logo" ></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
