<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Angel | SotoSeattle]]></title>
  <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/categories/angel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-03-11T16:35:56-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Javier Soto]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hunting Tips]]></title>
    <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2017/03/11/Hunting-Tips/"/>
    <updated>2017-03-11T12:00:40-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2017/03/11/Hunting-Tips</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Last week I had the pleasure to attend the Angel Capital Association Northwest Regional Meeting in Portland, Oregon. I specially enjoyed the atmosphere of camaraderie and common effort to make the PNW a vibrant and healthy startup ecosystem.</p>

<p>A specially interesting talk was given by Rob Wiltbank, CEO of Galois and Professor of Entrepreneurship at Willamette University. The following is a bastardization of his ideas for my investing purposes:</p>

<!--more-->

<h3 id="understand-your-limits">Understand Your Limits</h3>

<p>Investors are good enough at differentiating the losing propositions (&lt;1x) from the rest. That means that while experience, knowledge and due diligence can help investors filter out the bad apples, we cannot seem to differentiate among the winning bets. We cannot seem to be able to figure out which investments will provide the highest returns (&gt;30x) among them all. For each selected investment, we can only be sure (up to a point) that it may not fail, not that it will provide a better return than its portfolio peers.</p>

<h3 id="adjust-expectations">Adjust Expectations</h3>

<p>A sobering fact when factoring in success scenarios is that most acquisitions (80%) of startups by public companies are for less than \$50M. If your portfolio is based on modelling all exits at the \$150M watermark you are up for a surprise. When modeling exit paths and expected returns, adjust them according to realistic probabilities.</p>

<p>Also, on the average, bad investments are short lived (less than 3 years), low return ones (1-5x) have an average life of 3 years, and the best ones ones come to roost the last (average 6/8 years), with the best exits at years 6 and 7, and later ones trailing off. Again, averages are tricky but don’t dismiss them.</p>

<h3 id="timing-matters">Timing Matters</h3>

<p>The business cycle impacts returns. The length of the business cycle (7 - 8 year) is similar to  the life horizon of our standard investments, so it is not the same to invest in a peak as in a valley. We’ll do better if we enter right after a cycle bust, because our investments will come to roost at the next peak, providing exit valuations under optimistic conditions. Conversely, if we invest in the peak, what could have been a 5-10x in good times, can become a 1-5x. When comparing studies from 2005 and 2012 this explains the fluctuation of the total percentage of poor returns (&lt;1x) which can fluctuate between 70% and 50%.</p>

<p>Interestingly enough, homeruns remain constant across cycles, and 10% of exits give you approx 90% of the value independent of business cycle timing. These homeruns exit in 6 to 8 years, so the better we time them the better for us.</p>

<h3 id="price-matters">Price Matters</h3>

<p>The Valuation at which we invest matters. Yes, it may be immaterial for homeruns due to the outsized outcome in comparison to the entry point, but it is not the same, when selling at 30, to have bought at 10 than 3. And since we cannot ascertain which ones will be homeruns, or even differentiate between 1-5x from 5-10x, we have an incentive to price them all downwards.</p>

<p>By the way, so far the data analyzed shows that price/valuation has no predictive power for returns at our stage of investing. And we still don’t know when this threshold is crossed (in which financing round price becomes predictor). So don’t sweat it.</p>

<h3 id="good-is-not-enough">Good is not enough</h3>

<p>Additionally, given that, for most of our portfolio, exits are most probable in the \$20M - \$50M range, we should avoid capped opportunities, companies that although offer us a good investment opportunity in risk/return terms, still we expect them to exit at low valuations. An example is a viable company in a small market that we believe will exit at \$20M. We should aim to overweight our portfolio with big game, outsized opportunities, and potential homeruns.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<hr />

<p><br /></p>

<p>A sensible strategy is to focus on avoiding bad bets (a proxy signal: they survive 3 years) and focusing on startups that can make a sizeable difference, uncapped in potential and targeting big enough market opportunities. This will translate in a lot of ducklings that offer &gt;1x returns, among them (hopefully) some still untransformed swans. Time will tell, the low returns will become nice fat ducks in 3 to 6 years, and those that live more than 6y (necessary condition yet not sufficient), may become our homeruns.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Founder Forecasts: a double-edged sword]]></title>
    <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/12/12/Promises/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-12T12:14:40-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/12/12/Promises</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>It is generally accepted that startups’ financial forecasts are more like a sailing bearing than a walkable path, a promise than an oath, optimistic intentions than pragmatic expectations.</p>

<p>I beg to differ.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Don’t get me wrong, I don’t care about the 5 or 10 year projections. The hockey stick meme is more an excuse to surface the underlying assumptions that justify the scalability of the business model, than a serious forecast.</p>

<p>But I do care about the short term, specially the next 12 to 18 months until the next milestone. Knowing what you can achieve in the next year signals more than diligence and knowledge (of market and go to market plan). It spells out self-awareness of the founder and team’s capabilities in what matters, their ability to engage, sell and fulfill.</p>

<p>If the founder is nonchalant about the short term, if orders of magnitudes are tossed around and changed on a whim, if looking back the need-to-pivot argument looks like a nervous tick, I’ll lose heart and attention.</p>

<p>The 12 month forecast is a soft-contract and breaking it should only be explained by exogenous factors. Factors not only beyond the control of the founders, but outside their radar from the start (and with good reason if so). If they could have been anticipated, they should have been factored in and stated from the start.</p>

<p>As a founder, try to treat your investors like you treat your customers. You don’t expect to say to your customers “hey, sorry the product didn’t do what we said it would, you know, it was a beta, and… stuff happens”. I know it is a caricaturization, but make it a guiding principle to under promise and over deliver, to everybody. It will be your most effective branding.</p>

<p>As investors, we fill the vacuum of uncertainty with unspoken and untested assumptions. Bad short term forecasts are specially dangerous because they generate all kinds of wrong assumptions. And when these are proven wrong, all that remains standing is the founder who gave her word.</p>

<p>Investors will look at what was forecasted in the round before, and will evaluate the founder on both: how grounded her estimates were and how well did she fulfilled her promises.</p>

<p>In a setting where uncertainty is high and facts are few, forecasts become soft promises that bind. If kept, they build trust. If broken, they taint.</p>

<p>A startup that goes beyond the forecasts and delivers more than promised, stands head and shoulders above the pack.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Gazelles and Unicorns]]></title>
    <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/11/18/Unicorns/"/>
    <updated>2016-11-18T12:14:40-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/11/18/Unicorns</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In StartupLand there are two markedly different types of beasts: gazelles and unicorns.</p>

<p>As investor’s, how should we analyze each type?</p>

<p><img class="center" src="/images/nov16/gazcorn.png" width="500"></p>

<!--more-->
<p>Here are some concepts that I liberally took from an ACA (Angel Capital Association) webinar given by Keyvan Firouzi’s (Gust’s Director Valuation Services).</p>

<p><em>Gazelles</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>Expected Returns with multiples between 1x and 30x.</li>
  <li>On average, they will comprise 30% of a diversified portfolio.</li>
  <li>The key drivers to achieve these returns depend on execution, steady performance, and incremental improvements.</li>
  <li>Due diligence matters, not only team but the whole panoply.</li>
  <li>Right assessment of pre money valuation matters.</li>
  <li>Deal terms and subsequent financing rounds matters too for its dilutive effect.</li>
  <li>A too high pre money valuation signals a misalignment between founders and investors.</li>
  <li>Pre money Valuation, Ask and Stage must be aligned too.</li>
</ul>

<p><em>Unicorns</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>Returns &gt; 30x</li>
  <li>In the average, it will comprise just 2% of a diversified portfolio.</li>
  <li>The key driver is the occurrence of major technological, social, geographic-specific cultural and/or economical shifts.</li>
  <li>These shifts take years in the making before a commercial opportunity arrives.</li>
  <li>Due diligence is specially important assessing <em>timing</em> and scope of shift, as well as the quality of team to navigate it.</li>
  <li>Pre money valuation is not a key input. Don’t lose sleep.</li>
</ul>

<p>In Summary for Unicorns ask Why now? (timing) and Why you? (Team). For Gazelles, the questions are more operational so ask a lot of Who, What, Why, and Hows?</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Psyc Founders Out]]></title>
    <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/06/18/Founders/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-18T13:14:40-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/06/18/Founders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In terms of relative weight, when investing in a startup, the quality of management and specifically of the Founder/CEO is the single most important driver of success. It is not the only one, many other pieces need to fit together too, but the caliber of the head of the organization is the main necessary condition.</p>

<!--more-->

<p><img class="right" src="/images/jun16/handrabbit.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>Zeroing in the Founders. There are many aspects to consider when analyzing the leadership of a startup, and as investors we tend to fall into the false complacency of factual information. If something can be quantified or at least backed up by facts, then we have a good proxy to analyze, compare and assess. Again, this data is all good and dandy, but for me it just satisfies a necessary condition, it is not sufficient.</p>

<p>Beyond the facts of a Founder’s profile there is a personality. And beyond the personality there are things as immaterial and diffuse as motivations, goals and perspectives. These are more difficult to assess because they are subjective in nature and do not conform to easy typecasting.</p>

<p>I do believe that many investors can assess facts and crunch numbers with great accuracy, so there is little competitive margin to be gained by those of us who do not come from Lake Wobegon. I believe that there is a lot of money to be made by correctly assessing the imponderables, the subjective and the ill defined.</p>

<p><em>Founder’s Obssession</em></p>

<p>To me, the single most important characteristic. Is the Founder obsessed about her product, the problem and its customers? Does she fall asleep thinking about the venture? Does she compulsively engage with customers? Where does she get her best ideas (e.g. the shower)? When you ask a question, does it show that she has thought about it before in detail? Don’t confound a nervous personality and a certain degree of hyperactivity with what I mean by obsession. The obsession I talk about comes through as energy that exudes from every pore in a casual conversation.</p>

<p><em>Founder’s Motivation</em></p>

<p>As a Founder, why do it? Why go through all the pains and stresses? Behind the facade of personal drive and ambition, the real reasons that propel a Founder may be varied. Some perceived weaknesses can become great sources of strength, yet others can be ticking bombs in disguise that will doom the enterprise later on.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Is she trying to prove something to herself? Or is she trying to measure up in someone’s eyes?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>As a career change, does it carry a sense of entitlement born out of a successful run in a corporate environment or upbringing?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Is that drive to connect with others (investors, clients, employees) a personality trait borne out of empathy and discipline? Or is it a reflection of a deeper need to be in the spotlight (i.e. narcissistic tendencies)?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Her superlative personality shows in facts like: she climbed the 7 tallest mountains or likes to parachute on Sundays. But are these a reflection of personal drive or are they symptoms of an inability to stay put and a pathological need to push the limits? I personally want risk takers, not testosterone-unhinged thrill-seekers.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>Founder’s POV</em></p>

<p>As investors we analyze the startup from the little understanding of the company that we slowly accumulate in a short period of time. The whats, whys and hows. From the outside. We do not tend to see things as they are; but as we are. From our personal experience and point of view.</p>

<p>For all the talk about understanding customers needs and putting ourselves in other’s peoples shoes, we as investors should walk the walk and try to see through the Founder’s eyes. It is valuable to complement our own understanding with an understanding of how the Founder actually thinks about the startup. Does she sees things the way we do? Does she connect the dots and evaluate the different parts in the same way we do?</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>What does she care about most? What do her actions tell us about how her behaviour towards the different stakeholders? (employees, investors, clients).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>What is she afraid of? For sure she has thought about failure scenarios. What are her real barriers to exit? Not only material but reputational. For some, a failure with somebody else’s money can be seen as a badge of honor in a startup career, an experiential stepping stone or a sabbatical.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Beyond engaging in conversation with Founders, the materials they present can tell a story too. Looking past the abused business jargon there is always a choice when selecting ideas and words. Like witnesses interviewed by the Police, people cannot help themselves and end up giving clues of what they really think, fear and motivates them. Up to what degree is the Founder aware of this? Awareness is a plus in my book, but how do you tell the self-aware from the smooth-operator?</p>

    <p>Additionally, another source of insight are the financial projections that the Founders prepare. As future forecasts of revenues,  they are by nature not very useful. But sometimes the expenditure structure and assumptions can convey quite a lot about how the Founders understand their company today.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>Last Thoughts</em></p>

<p>There is no need to be cynical or negative about all this. My point is that we need to step away from the hyped up profiles and personal stories of Founders, and instead see them anew as fleshed out humans. No startup is perfect, no Investor is perfect, and no Founder is perfect either. We just need to make sure that our assumptions, understanding and incentives are in line with those of the Founders, and that, overall, the startup story is consistent, coherent and makes sense across its many dimensions.</p>

<p>I leave to the reader the exercise of figuring out what this post says about me and how I see Angel Investing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
