<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Angel | SotoSeattle]]></title>
  <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/categories/angel/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-06-18T13:20:44-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Javier Soto]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Psyc Founders Out]]></title>
    <link href="http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/06/18/Founders/"/>
    <updated>2016-06-18T13:14:40-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://sotoseattle.github.io/blog/2016/06/18/Founders</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In terms of relative weight, when investing in a startup, the quality of management and specifically of the Founder/CEO is the single most important driver of success. It is not the only one, many other pieces need to fit together too, but the caliber of the head of the organization is the main necessary condition.</p>

<!--more-->

<p><img class="right" src="/images/jun16/handrabbit.jpg" width="300"></p>

<p>Zeroing in the Founders, there are many aspects to consider when analyzing the leadership of a startup, and as investors we tend to fall into the false complacency of factual information. If something can be quantified or at least backed up by facts, then we have a good proxy to analyze, compare and assess. Again, these types of variables are all great and dandy, but for me they are just a necessary condition, not sufficient.</p>

<p>Beyond the facts of a Founder’s profile there is a personality, and beyond the personality there are things as immaterial and diffuse as motivations, goals and perspectives. These are more difficult to assess because they are subjective in nature and do not conform to easy typecasting.</p>

<p>I do believe that many investors can assess facts and crunch numbers with greater accuracy, so there is little competitive advantage there to be gained by those of us who are not from Lake Wobegon. But I also believe that there is a lot of money to be made by correctly assessing the imponderables, the subjective and the ill defined.</p>

<p><em>Founder’s Motivation</em></p>

<p>Why do it? Why go through all the pains and stresses? Behind a facade of drive the real reasons that propel a Founder may be varied. Some perceived weaknesses can become great sources of strength, yet others can be ticking bombs that will doom the enterprise down the road.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Is she trying to prove something to herself? Or is she trying to measure up in someone’s eyes? Is she self aware of her own motivations? No need to be Zen, just wise enough or able enough to listen outside of one’s bubble.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>If this is a career change, does it carry a sense of entitlement born out of a successful career in a corporate environment or upbringing?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Is that drive to connect with others (investors, clients, employees) a personality trait borne out of empathy and discipline, or is it a reflection of a deeper need to be in the spotlight (i.e. narcissistic tendencies)?</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>The fact that she climbed the 7 tallest mountains or likes to parachute on Sundays, is it a reflection of drive or is it of a deeper inability to stay put, and a pathological need to push the limits? I want risk takers, not testosterone-unhinged thrill-seekers.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p><em>Founder’s POV</em></p>

<p>For all the talk about understanding customers and putting on other’s peoples shoes (gross), we as investors should walk the walk and try to see through the Founder’s eyes. This is closely related to the previous point of understanding the Founder’s motivations.</p>

<p>As investors we analyze the startup from the little understanding we slowly accumulate of the company in a short period of time. The whats, whys and hows. From the outside. It is only natural and logical. Furthermore, and at the expense of sounding corny, we do not tend to see things as they are; but as we are. From our personal experience and point of view.</p>

<p>I think it is valuable to complement this with an understanding of how the Founder actually thinks about the startup. Does she sees things the way we do? Does she connect the dots and evaluate the different parts in the same way we do?</p>

<p>What does she care about most? What do her actions tell us about how she behaves towards the interests of the different stakeholders? (employees, investors, clients).</p>

<p>What is she afraid of? For sure she has thought about failure scenarios. What are her real barriers to exit? Not only material but reputational. For some, a failure with somebody else’s money can be seen a badge of honor in a startup career, an experiential stepping stone or a sabbatical.</p>

<p>Beyond engaging in conversation with Founders, the materials they present can tell a story too. Discounting the abused business jargon there is always a choice when selecting ideas and words. Like witnesses interviewed by the police, we cannot help ourselves and end up giving clues of what we really think, fear and motivates us. Up to what degree is the Founder aware of this? Awareness is a plus in my book, but how do you tell the self aware from the smooth operator?</p>

<p>Additionally, I have found that another source of insight is the financial projections the Founders prepare. As future forecasting they are by nature not very useful, but sometimes they say quite a lot about how the Founders understand their company today.</p>

<p><em>Last Thoughts</em></p>

<p>There is no need to be cynical or negative about all this. My point is that we need to step away from the marketed and hyped profiles of Founders of today and see them as fleshed out humans. No startup is perfect, and no Founder is perfect either. We just need to make sure that our assumptions, understanding and incentives are in line with those of the Founders, and that, overall, the startup story is consistent, coherent and makes sense across its many dimensions.</p>

<p>I leave to the reader the exercise of figuring out what this post says about me and about how I see Angel Investing.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
